<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reward of Christian patience as it was discover'd in a sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. Tho. Badland, a nonconforming minister at Kedderminster / by R. White ...</title>
            <author>White, Richard, b. 1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38599</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17805136</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17805136</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106635</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65767)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106635)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1109:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reward of Christian patience as it was discover'd in a sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. Tho. Badland, a nonconforming minister at Kedderminster / by R. White ...</title>
                  <author>White, Richard, b. 1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within mourning borders.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Badland, Tho. --  (Thomas)</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106635:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106635:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Reward of Chriſtian Patience:</hi> As it was Diſcover'd in a SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL OF <hi rend="blackletterType">Mr. Tho. Badland,</hi> A Nonconforming Miniſter at <hi>KEDDERMINSTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>R. WHITE,</hi> B. D. And Vicar of <hi>Kedderminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chappel.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106635:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106635:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis following Diſcourſe being delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before a Numerous Congregation both of Miniſters and People, both Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts and Nonconformiſts, about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>February</hi> laſt; had the good hap to meet with a general Acceptation from the Auditory then preſent, and therefore I am hereby encouraged to make it more publick; hoping that it may Conduce to the making of
<pb facs="tcp:106635:3"/>ſome good Impreſſions upon thoſe that ſhall peruſe it, under what denomination ſoever they are rank't: I commend it and thee to the grace of God, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug. 22. 1693.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, in our Common Saviour,</hi> R. WHITE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106635:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JAMES 1. xii.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſſed is the Man that endureth tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for when he is tried, he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the crown of life which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Have choſen theſe Words to be the Subject of my preſent Diſcourſe, becauſe they bear an eſpecial ſuitableneſs to the Caſe of that Perſon, who hath given occaſion for this preſent Solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as will more fully appear in the Proceſs of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The words contain a compleat ſenſe within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and therefore I ſhall not trouble you or my ſelf, with the Conſideration of the Coherence and Relation which they may bear with that which goes before, or follows after.</p>
            <p>In the words you may take notice, 1. Of a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal Aſſertion, laid down in the firſt part of the Words, <hi>Bleſſed is the man, that endureth temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of the Proof and Evidence that is further given to this Aſſertion, in the following words;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106635:4"/>
               <hi>for when he is tryed, he ſhall receive the Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt General, the Doctrinal Aſſertion that is here laid down, and that you have in theſe words; <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth Temptation;</hi> wherein for orders ſake, we may far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take notice of theſe following Particulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subject or Perſon ſpoken of, together with the Character that is given of him; <hi>'tis the man that endureth Temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The predicate, or what is aſſerted of him, declaring his happy State and Condition, <hi>he's a bleſſed man; Bleſſed is the man that endureth Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Then as to the ſubject here ſpoken of and characterized, <hi>it is the man that endureth Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> for the explaining of this I muſt deſcend to two particulars: 1. To explain what's here to be underſtood by <hi>Temptation:</hi> 2. What 'tis for a man to endure <hi>Temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Then I am to explain, what is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood here by <hi>Temptation.</hi> The <hi>Greek</hi> word here uſed is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which plainly is derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies to explore, or ſearch, or make
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106635:4"/>trial; ſo that the word in the general ſenſe of it, denotes no more then ſomething whereby trial is made of a Perſon; and ſo far <hi>Temptation</hi> is a thing Adiapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and capable either of good or evil, to explore or make trial or diſcovery of a Perſon may be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or evil, according to the intent and deſign of it, and other Circumſtances that may attend it. 1. Sometimes to explore and try a Perſon of whom we are in doubt, may be warrantable enough, ſo it be done by fair and juſt Means and Methods; whence 'tis that this tempting, by way of trial and explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is ſometimes attributed to God Himſelf; not as if he could improve in Knowledge of any Perſon, by any ſuch trial and exploration, for His Knowledge is Omniſcience, and tis impoſſible by any trial or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploration, to make it more perfect then 'tis in itſelf. <hi>He Searcheth the hearts, and tries the reins of men, and knows their thoughts long before.</hi> The reaſon therefore of this exploration and trial, which God makes of men at any time, is thereby to diſcover that to themſelves or others, which though fully known to himſelf, yet was not before ſo clearly known to them. Thus in this ſenſe God is ſaid to tempt <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 22.1. that is, he laid ſuch a commandment upon him, even the commandment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106635:5"/>which required him to Sacrifice his only Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> with his own hands, as ſhould try him and diſcover him to the utmoſt, and by Obedience to which he would fully diſcover that true principle of the fear of God, which was fixed in him. Whence, when <hi>Abraham</hi> expreſt his readineſs to perform this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, God ſaith, <hi>now I know that thou feareſt God, ſeeing thou haſt not witheld thy Son, thine only Son from me, v.</hi> 12. Now I know; not as if God could be Ignorant of this before, who is the ſearcher of all Hearts, and underſtandeth all the Imaginations of the Thoughts; but it ſignifies that. God knew this now by trial and exploration, and he knew it ſo as to make a clear diſcovery of it to <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf for his comfort, and to the Church in all Ages and Succeſſions, in order to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s honour, and to incourage others to an imitation of this Father of the Faithful.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometimes and moſt generally temptations do ſignify ſuch kind of trials, as have not only ſome ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency through the corruption of Men, to draw them to ſin, but are alſo intended by the parties that make uſe of them, as means whereby to ſeduce men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Tranſgreſſions againſt God, that ſo they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come liable to the miſeries threatned in his Law, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106635:5"/>the tranſgreſſors of it; in this ſence, <hi>God is not tempted of evil, neither tempteth he any man;</hi> as our Apoſtle ſaith in the Verſe following my Text: God never deſigns in any of theſe trials or explora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which he makes of Men to draw them to ſin; but he leaves them it may be, to the free Motions of their own Wills, and theſe being corrupted with Luſt and Inordinate Appetites, are apt to be ſeduc't to cloſe with what is offered in the Temptation, ſo far as thereby to run upon the breach of God's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; in this ſence every man when he is Tempted, <hi>is drawn away of his own luſts and inticed,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>v.</hi> 14. 'Tis only the Devil the Apoſtate Angels, and men as their Inſtruments, that can be Tempters in this ſcenſe, theſe only can offer any thing to the Perſons Tempted, with this deſign to draw them into ſin thereby; and even good men may unawares be made uſe of by Satan, as Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this matter; whence when <hi>Peter</hi> would adviſe our Saviour, to ſave himſelf from thoſe Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, which he declared would light upon him; our Saviour rebukt him ſeverely for it, and call'd him Satan, as being his inſtrument in this matter: <hi>Get thee behind me Satan, for thou ſavoureſt not the things that be of God, but the things that be of men,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106635:6"/>Mat.</hi> 16.23. Now 'tis further to be obſerved in this matter, that 1. As there is ſcarce any Perſon, ſo there is ſcarce any thing but may be made uſe of as an Inſtrument by <hi>Satan,</hi> to draw men into ſin: All things that are grateful to our Appetite, he can make uſe of as Bates to allure men to Sin, in order to the obtaining of them. All things that are adverſe and grievous to us, he can make uſe of as means to fright us from Obedience to Gods Will and Commandments; yea ſometimes he makes uſe of the very Gifts and Graces, with which men may be Endowed, to become a Snare and an occaſion of Pride, and Security unto them; and ſo as Lime Twigs whereby to draw and allure them to ſin. But yet 2. Perſecutions and Afflictions, and ſuch things as are grievous to our Tender Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are thoſe things which the Apoſtle here e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially means by <hi>Temptations,</hi> as being eſpecially thoſe things whereby men are wont to be tried, whether or no they will perſiſt in a courſe of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the will of God to the end, and whereby <hi>Satan</hi> particularly deſigns to draw men into Sin; that Afflictions and Perſecutions are here eſpecially to be underſtood by Temptations, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, becauſe of the Expreſſion of enduring them,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106635:6"/>which (as you will hear more by and by) denotes ſomething of Patience and Chriſtian Fortitude, which are the Graces and Vertues, that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant about and wont to be exerciſed by Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Perſecutions; and this may ſerve for the explaining of the firſt Particular propounded, which was, what is here to be underſtood by <hi>Temptations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I proceed now to ſhew what it is for a Man to endure Temptations; in Anſwer to which you may take theſe following Particulars: 1. This en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during of Temptations doth ſignifie a Willingneſs and Readineſs to ſuffer Afflictions and Perſecutions, yea an Actual Suffering of them, and that even to the Death, rather then for the avoiding of them, to be guilty of the Commiſſion of any known Sin. 'Tis true, Afflictions and Perſecutions are not things Eligible and Deſirable in Themſelves. 'Tis Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, yea our Duty to endeavour to avoid them, and get rid of them by all honeſt and lawful ways and methods; 'tis plain from hence, becauſe they are Temptations; and as we are to Pray unto God <hi>not to lead us into Temptation,</hi> ſo we are by all honeſt and lawful means, to endeavour to avoid and get rid of Perſecutions and Afflictions, as being thoſe things which are great Trials of our Conſtancy, &amp; may, if we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106635:7"/>have not the greater Care, be occaſions of Sin unto us; Affliction and Perſecution are never to be choſen and embraced, but when they ſtand in competition with Sin, and then indeed they are to be choſen; when it comes to this Point, that we muſt either chooſe Sin or Suffering, the Caſe is plain, Suffering is to be choſen rather than Sin; according to that Rule, <hi>E malis minimum,</hi> of two Evils the leaſt is to be choſen. Now that Suffering, even the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Suffering is a leſs Evil than Sin, even the leaſt Sin, is plain hence that Sin is the procuring and deſerving cauſe of all Suffering; if there had been no ſin, there would have been no Suffering: All the Calamities, Woes and Miſeries, that any where appear in the World, yea and Death it ſelf came in at the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door of Sin: <hi>By one man ſin entred into the World, and Death by ſin, and ſo Death paſt over all men, for that all have ſinned,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom,</hi> 5.12. ſo that it muſt needs be, that ſince Sin is a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Evil then Suffering, when theſe come in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition together, ſo that we muſt either chooſe Sin on the one hand, or Suffering on the other; in this Caſe Suffering is to be choſen and ſubmitted to; and thus to chooſe and ſubmit to Suffering for the avoidance of Sin, is one great Inſtance, wherein
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106635:7"/>doth conſiſt this enduring of Temptation here mentioned: But 2. It denotes further ſomething of the manner of our ſubmitting to, and endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Afflictions and Perſecutions, that Patience and quiet Submiſſion to the Divine Will ought to be exerciſed therein.</p>
            <p>It becomes not Chriſtians when at any time they are under Afflictions in any kind, to be Tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Unquiet, both to themſelves and others about them, like a Wild-bull in a Net; but to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that a State of Affliction is a ſpecial Seaſon, wherein we are called upon to Exerciſe the Grace of Patience and to fortify our ſelves therein; from all thoſe Conſiderations that are apt to Conduce thereunto; as particularly 1. From a believing Conſideration of this, that Afflictions ariſe not out of the Duſt, but are directed to men by a ſpecial Providence; he that believes a Providence in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral can't doubt of this; <hi>Is there any evil in the City,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>and the Lord hath not done it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From a believing conſideration of this further, that God doth not delight in Mens Afflictions meerly for themſelves, that he doth not Afflict willingly, nor grieve the Sons of Men: He takes no more delight in Afflicting Men, eſpecially his own People, then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106635:8"/>the Father in Correcting his Child, or the Surgeon in Cutting and Lancing his Patient, that he intends all Afflictions to be Medicines, whereby to Purge away our Sins, and to bring us to Repentance, and Humiliation for them, and that 'tis in very Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Love, that he Afflicteth his People, and that there is ſome need of it one way or other, whenever he lays his Rod upon them, according to thoſe words of the Apoſtle, if need be; <hi>Ye are in heavineſs through manifold Temptations,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From a believing Conſideration of this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that God will continue the Affliction no longer then there is need of it, but that in due time he will quite remove the Rod from us, or us from it; and that He knows how to cauſe all things to work together for good, to them that love God, to them that are called according to his purpoſe: Theſe Truths and ſuch as theſe, are things which being real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed, and duely conſidered, are apt to quiet and compoſe the Spirits of Men under Afflictions, and to make them of a patient ſubmiſſive frame of Spirit, theſe are the things which muſt enable the Soul in a State of Affliction, to ſay heartily with <hi>Job, Shall we receive good at the hands of God, and ſhall we not receive evil;</hi> and to bleſs God and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106635:8"/>perſevere in the praiſing of him, even when we are under a State of Affliction, as well as when we are compaſt about with Proſperity; ſaying again with <hi>Job, The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> This pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and quiet Submiſſion to the afflicting hand of God, as it doth ariſe from the Exerciſe of Faith, is likewiſe included in this enduring Affliction here ſpoken of, ſo that by this time you may conclude who it is that is the Man, that endureth Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he is one that chooſeth Suffering rather then known Sin, when he's under a State of Suffering, is careful to exerciſe Patience, and quiet Submiſſion to the hand of God, as being by Faith perſwaded that God hath an Hand in all theſe matters, <hi>and that whom God loveth he chaſtens, and ſcourgeth every Son whom he receiveth,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6. And thus you have had the Subject of this doctrinal Aſſertion, that is contained in my Text, ſufficiently explained unto you: Now</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of this Perſon that is thus qualified, 'tis aſſerted that he is a bleſſed man; <hi>Bleſſed is the Man that endureth Temptation:</hi> I need not ſtand long to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the nature of true Bleſſedneſs, let it ſuffice for the preſent, that true bleſſedneſs ſo far as attaina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106635:9"/>here in this World, conſiſts in the Love and Favour of God through Chriſt, and in a Right and Title to the Happineſs of Heaven, and to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God in that other World; this is the utmoſt of that Bleſſedneſs, which a Man on this ſide Heaven is capable of, and which every one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of here below, that is a true Penitent and and a ſound Believer. That which I ſhall further deſcend unto, ſhall be to ſhew and prove in ſome Particulars, that the Man that endureth Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is indeed an Happy and a Bleſſed Man: And this will be evident if we conſider, 1. That this is plainly aſſerted concerning a patient enduring of ſome kind of Afflictions and Temptations, I mean Perſecution for Righteouſneſs ſake, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing patiently ſubmitted to, to the end, do certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give a Right and Title to true bleſſedneſs; thus ſaith our Saviour who is Truth it ſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.10. <hi>&amp;c. Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven: Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil of you falſely for my ſake; rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven, for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106635:9"/>
            <p>Now though Perſecutions for Righteouſneſs ſake are that ſort of Afflictions, which being choſen and ſubmitted to, rather then Men will run into known and wilful Sin, for the avoiding of them, do give a Man eminently a Title to Happineſs and Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and are likewiſe thoſe Temptations, that are here eſpecially to be underſtood in this Text, yet any other Affliction, which being alſo a Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſin, yet is ſo endured with Patience and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, out of a Principle of Faith in God through Chriſt, as that the Temptation doth not finally prevail upon the Soul, muſt ſuitably be concluded in a parity of Reaſon, to give a Right and Title to true Bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us further conſider, that this enduring Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as it hath been before explained, doth car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it neceſſarily the exerciſe of Grace, of Faith and Patience, and quiet Submiſſion to the Divine Will, and a Reſolution to embrace a Suffering State and Condition, rather then to Sin againſt God, all this hath been already proved. Now it muſt needs follow, that he that doth in this right man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner endure Temptations, is an Happy and Bleſſed Perſon; he muſt needs be intereſſed in the ſpecial Love and Favour of God, he muſt needs have a right
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106635:10"/>to pardon of Sin and everlaſting Life; for this is the certain condition of every truely gracious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of every one who hath the Image of God, reimplanted upon his Soul, which conſiſts in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and true holineſs, and ſheweth forth the power of it, in his Life and Converſation. When 'tis here ſaid, <hi>that bleſſed is the man that endureth Temptation,</hi> 'tis not hereby to be underſtood, that every one who ſuffers Affliction here in this World, hath forthwith hereupon a Right and Title to Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs in that other World, for this is certainly falſe; Men may be Afflicted with deep and ſore Poverty, and many are through the whole courſe of their lives, and yet ſuch is their ſinfulneſs, their ſottiſh Ignorance, and careleſneſs of the Welfare of their Souls, that we have no reaſon to think or believe that they are likely to be happy and bleſſed in that other World. But when Men do endure Afflictions and Temptations, ſo as to exerciſe the Grace of God under them, by choſing Affliction rather then Sin, by the exerciſe of Faith and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and quiet Submiſſion to the Will of God; this doth indeed clearly evidence, that they have a Right and Title to true Bleſſedneſs, becauſe it doth plainly diſcover, that they are endowed with the ſaving Grace of God in their Souls.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106635:10"/>
            <p n="3">3. And laſtly, The laſt evidence that I ſhall give of the Truth of this, that the Man is bleſſed that endureth Temptation, ſhall be taken from the Reaſon and Evidence, which the Apoſtle gives of this matter here in my Text; <hi>for when he's tried he ſhall receive the Crown of Life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love Him;</hi> in which words we have a plain demonſtration of the truth of what is ſaid before, that the Man is bleſſed that endureth Temptation; and I ſhall conſider the words briefly in theſe following Particulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. We have here the evidence, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle gives, whereby it may appear that ſuch a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is bleſſed, it conſiſts in theſe words, <hi>he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Crown of Life,</hi> that is, he ſhall be made partaker of the Happineſs of Heaven, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in a perfection of Holineſs, and a full and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted enjoyment of God in Glory and Bliſs, together with a Separation for ever of every thing, that may any way prove a diſturbance to the Soul. In that State all Tears ſhall be wiped away from the Eyes of Believers, and all the remainders of Sin ſhall be purged away from their Souls, yea and all Temptations to Sin, ſhall for ever ceaſe; for the Tempter is for ever caſt out thence, he ſhall never
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106635:11"/>ſhoot one of his Fiery Darts in thither, tho' he ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crept into the Earthly Paradice, yet he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have any admiſſion into the Heavenly: To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, the buſineſs of Holy Souls will be, to be for ever enjoying, and bleſſing, and praiſing God, and to be for ever Happy in the Enjoyment of him. Now this bleſſed State which ſuch ſhall partake of, is here called the Crown of Life: Crowns we know are Splendid attractive things, ſuch as for the attaining of which Men will too often venture their Lives, yea their very Souls, and therefore becauſe they are an expreſſion of the chiefeſt of Enjoyments, which this World doth afford, they are made uſe of to expreſs that Superlative hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, which is to be enjoyed in Heaven: And this is yet further hinted and ſet forth from hence, that 'tis called <hi>a Crown of Life.</hi> The Crowns which this lower World doth afford, are but corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Crowns, Kingdoms as well as Kings, are here below liable to Ruine and Mortality; but the Crown which is here ſpoken of, is an Incorruptible Crown, 'tis all made of Amarants, 'tis Everlaſting, 'tis a Crown of Life, Death can not touch it, any more than 'tis poſſible for Death to become Life; Hence 'tis ſuitably called an <hi>Inheritance, Incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106635:11"/>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled that Fadeth not away,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. Thoſe that ſhall poſſeſs this Crown, are Immortal in their Souls, and ſhall be made Immortal in their Bodies; that God whoſe enjoyment makes Heaven, is the God who is yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever, who only hath Immortality and there ſhall be an everlaſting Union between God, who is to be enjoyed, and the Souls that are once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the enjoyment of him in Heaven; from whence it muſt needs follow, that the Happineſs to be enjoyed by the Saints in Heaven, is indeed a Crown of Life, an Everlaſting Crown, an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that never fadeth away. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have in theſe Words further, the reaſon the Apoſtle gives, why ſo it is, <hi>That they that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Temptation ſhall enjoy the Crown of Life,</hi> and that conſiſts in the laſt words, 'tis no other then what God hath promiſed to them that Love Him: If they that Love God above all, and take him for their Portion, and Everlaſting Reſting Place, ſhall enjoy this Crown of Life; if God who is true to his Word, and faithful to his Promiſe, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed this Crown to all ſuch, then certainly it will follow, that they who endure Temptation ſhall enjoy this Crown; for they that endure Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106635:12"/>that is, that chooſe Suffering and Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea Death it ſelf rather then wilful Sin, and that do eye God by Faith and Patience, and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit to the Divine Will, in all their Sufferings, theſe muſt needs be Perſons who do truly Love God above all, and have choſen him for their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Portion and Bleſſedneſs, and therefore they muſt needs be the Perſons that ſhall enjoy the Crown of Life. But</p>
            <p n="3">3. And laſtly, We have further in theſe Words, the limitation of Time, when ſuch Perſons ſhall come to the enjoyment of this Crown of Life; after they are tried, for when he is tried he ſhall receive the Crown of Life. After that his Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs hath been tried, and approved by Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Perſecutions, and Temptations, after it hath been made appear, that his Trials and Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations could not prevail with him to forſake God, and Apoſtatize from him, then he ſhall receive the Crown of Life. This is the uſual way and method of God, even that way which he appointed for his own Son, to make the Croſs to be the way to the Crown; to try his Servants firſt by Afflictions and Sufferings, and then to receive them to Glory, and give them the Crown of Life; but when this is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106635:12"/>done, when he hath ſufficiently tried and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Servants, (and he alone knows when this is ſufficiently done) then they ſhall receive the Crown of Life, <hi>which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him;</hi> which is the laſt Conſideration, whence it doth appear, that ſuch Perſons as do thus endure Afflictions and Temptations, are happy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Perſons.</p>
            <p>Now laſtly, For the Uſe and Improvement of what hath been ſpoken, 1. It teacheth us, how to behave our ſelves with relation to Afflictions and Perſecutions, which we may meet with in the courſe of our Lives, on the one hand, we ſhould not court them, or run our ſelves wilfully into them, that's unwarrantable, becauſe at beſt they are Trials and Temptations, apt to ſhake our Conſtancy, and to hurry us into ſome meaſure of Sin againſt God. On the other hand, we ſhould not be over much prejudic'd againſt them, but rather chooſe Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Perſecutions, then a courſe of known and wilful Sin, and when we are under Afflictions behave ourſelves with that Patience and quiet Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Will of God, which becomes Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that live by Faith, and not by Senſe meerly: the reaſon of all this is plain, becauſe that Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106635:13"/>when thus choſen and endured, do but prepare and fit the Soul, for eternal Happineſs and Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; he is the bleſſed Man that thus endureth Temptation, for when he hath been tried he ſhall receive the Crown of Life.</p>
            <p>We may hence comfort our ſelves with relation to the death and departure of ſuch Friends, who having it may be, been exerciſed with great Afflictions and Temptations, yet have endured them, have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted with any good meaſure of Patience to the Will of God in them, and this from a Principle of Repentance, and Faith in the Mercy of God thro' Chriſt; concerning ſuch we have much reaſon to comfort our ſelves with hopes, that by their death they are entred into a State of Bleſſedneſs, that God having ſufficiently tried them, and purified them in the Furnace of Affliction, hath ſuitably by Death received them to that Place and State, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they enjoy the Crown of Life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that Love Him. More particularly there ſeems to be in the Words, a clear repreſentation of the Caſe of our deceaſed Friend, as will appear more fully in theſe following parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:106635:13"/>
            <p n="1">1. He was one that hath for many Years, been Tutored by God in the School of Affliction, it hath been his Portion to be exerciſed with many Trials and Temptations; beſides ſeveral Afflictions that are more ordinary, he hath for ſeveral Years been exerciſed, and of late more frequently than in former times, by thoſe two ſevere Diſeaſes, the Stone and the Gout, of which we may ſay, that whereas Diſeaſes are wont to be diſtinguiſht ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, into ſuch as are Acute, ſuch as are Sharp in the pains that attend them, but not of any long continuance, and ſuch as are Cronical of long continuance, but not attended with ſuch Sharp pains, yet theſe Diſeaſes may be eſteemed to be both Acute and Cronical too, Sharp in their pains, and long in their duration and continuance: His laſt Fit of the Stone, that which brought on that weakneſs, which ended in Death, was ſuch as had both the forementioned Circumſtances in it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing long, even extended to the length of about E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven days together, and very Acute too, being full of Sharp Pains and Dolours: and (at leaſt as ſome have thought) his other Diſeaſe the Gout did at laſt take its turn, as it was uſual formerly, and as 'tis ſuppoſed by peircing into his Bowels, put an end
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106635:14"/>to all his Pains and Dolours, by putting an end to his Life. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us conſider, for our own Edification as well as for his Honour, his Behaviour under all thoſe Afflictions which he laboured under: 1. As for his Behaviour under thoſe great pains which he was frequently viſited with; beſides the known and exemplary Holineſs and regularity of his Life for many Years in this place, of which all of you are ſufficient Witneſſes, and his conſtant attendance upon his Miniſtry, when at any time free from thoſe forementioned Diſtempers, yea, and ſometimes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when under the ſenſe and feeling of thoſe pains in ſome leſſer degree: That which I would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially recommend to your conſideration and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, is his ſignal Patience under all his great do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and his biting them in as it were, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in a great meaſure to himſelf; and when he had any lucid Intervals and Intermiſſions from Pain, he was apt preſently to ſhew a readineſs for profitable Diſcourſe and Converſation, as if what was paſt, had been quite forgotten, and he had not been under any expectations of more to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue; and this not out of a Principle of Stocal Apathy or unſenſibleneſs, for he fet his pains, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106635:14"/>ſometimes groaned under them, as others do; but out of a Principle of Faith and Heavenly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, he endured, as ſeeing him by an Eye of Faith, who is Inviſible to an Eye of Senſe; he had caſt Anchor within the Vail, and hereby came to enjoy that great meaſure of fixedneſs of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which was not eaſily overcome, even by his greateſt pains and dolours; this eminency of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Submiſſion to the Divine Will, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in other former Inſtances, ſo eſpecially in his laſt dolours and ſickneſs, particularly two days before his Death; how did he before ſeveral Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, lay out that little ſtrength that remained, in ſpeaking of God and Chriſt, and Heaven and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things, and this with a kind of Tranſport, and more than ordinary Earneſtneſs and Vigour of Spirit; and when he was put in mind to favour himſelf, becauſe of the great weakneſs of his Body, his Anſwer hereunto was quick and ſmart; Can I ſaith he, ſpeak too much for God? And even the Night before his Death, when his Speech had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore failed him for ſome Hours, and when by ſome ſigns, he declared his ſence and feeling of great pains that he laboured under, yet even then when he could utter nothing elſe, he was perceiv'd twice to repeat the word <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106635:15"/>
            <p n="2">2. As for his Behaviour for that long time, wherein he was withheld from the publick exerciſe of his Miniſtry, becauſe he could not with clearneſs of Judgment comply in every thing, which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Government (which was no doubt, a great Affliction to him) it was for the good temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and moderation of it, every whit as exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as the former inſtances of his Patience, under his pains and dolours were. He was no Friend to that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that running into extreams, which is ſo common amongſt us: But though he had as good Miniſterial Abilities as moſt others, yet he contented himſelf with that narrow ſcene of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherein he was placed, and therein endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red rather to be an healer of breaches, then to cauſe them to grow wider by exaſperation; that this was really true, I ſhall make out unto you by ſome few Inſtances: 1. From that temper and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of Judgment, which he expreſt in matters that are under Controverſy; one inſtance of which was, that in the matter of Reordination, which I apprehend, did prove as much a Remora and hindrance to his own Conformity, as any one thing did, yet he did in my hearing urge ſomething, that was very conſiderable by way of Apology, for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106635:15"/>thoſe that did ſubmit unto it: 2. Another inſtance, was his conſtant owning and ſavouring of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſtry, and that not only by his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant preſence at it, when in a capacity by means of health; but eſpecially by incouraging, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging others to a conſtant attendance upon it, by his frequent words to that purpoſe in private, and by recommending what had been ſpoken in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, to the Conſideration of his hearers, as many of you that are here preſent are able to teſtify; which I the rather mention, that it may ſerve as a ſtanding and grateful acknowledgment of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, which he gave from time to time to my Miniſtry. 3. and laſtly, Another inſtance was a paſſage which he uttered to ſome that watched with him, not many days before his Death; <hi>That in the choice of a Succeſſor to him in his Miniſtry, they ſhould labour to fix upon one of a quiet temper and moderate Principles, upon one that would rather be an healer than an enlarger of our breaches:</hi> Which Advice ſuitably it will become you to take care to obſerve, as you value that eaſineſs of Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which hath been hitherto preſerved amongſt us here in this place: And for the further enforcing of this Advice of his, give me leave to add a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106635:16"/>that he imparted to me, concerning the ſenſe of that Reverend Perſon, under whoſe conduct he was, when he came firſt to be an Inhabitant of this Town; to wit, <hi>That that Reverend Perſon judged that thoſe who were ſerious and ſober amongſt the Conformiſts, were much wiſer and more to be valued than thoſe forward Profeſſors, that were ſo ready upon account of little matters, to break the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and to Separate from the Communion of the Church e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by Law.</hi> And let me add this farther, that tho' that Reverend Perſon were himſelf a Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt, yet he did help to make men Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts by his Writings, ſome of which to my Knowledge, are now fixt in eminent Stations in the Church: And indeed he hath ſaid ſo much by way of Apology for the Conformiſts, in the compaſs of one Page, which you will find in the 46 Chap. of his <hi>Houſhold Catechiſm,</hi> in the beginning of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the 11 <hi>Queſtion,</hi> as gave occaſion to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Eminency to ſay in my hearing, that he wondred, <hi>how that reverend Perſon miſt being a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt.</hi> Theſe particulars I mention the rather in order to the confirming you againſt the thoughts of any ſuch Perſon in your choice, whoſe Principles may lead him to go up into the breach to no other
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106635:16"/>purpoſe, but to keep it open and to make it wider; to be ſure this will not be ſuitable to the temper of our Reverend Friend, now deceaſed; nay which is more, will not be ſuitable to the deſign of Chriſt in his laſt Prayer, <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.21. when he prayed for his Diſciples <hi>that they all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee; that they alſo may be one in us, that the World may believe that thou haſt ſent me;</hi> where 'tis plain, that our Saviour placeth much of the Evidence and Demonſtration of the Truth of the Goſpel, upon the Unity of Believers. And this may ſerve to evidence the Second Particular, to be very applicable to our deceaſed Friend, that he was one that endured, and acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf well under the Temptations with which he was tried and exerciſed, and therefore what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the</p>
            <p>3d. Place, But that we ſhould conclude, that he in particulars is intereſſed in that Bleſſedneſs, which in my Text by the Spirit of God, is intailed upon ſuch Perſons; when 'tis ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth Temptations, for when he is tried he ſhall receive the Crown of Life, which the Lord hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them that love him.</hi> Comfort your ſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and one another with theſe words.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
